CHARLES EAMES: An artist is
a title that you earn.
“艺术家”的名头是靠自己赢得的
And it's a little embarrassing
to hear
当人们自称“艺术家”的时候
people refer to themselves
听上去有点
as artists.
让人尴尬
It's like referring to
themselves as a genius.
就好像你自称“天才”一样
MAN: This was a man who was
a Merlin of curiosity.
这个男人对事物有着极大的好奇心
He was driven by his curiosity.
他亦被这种好奇心所驱使
MAN: We weren't sure
quite what he was.
我们尚且不知该如何定义他的身份
Was he an architect?
一位建筑家
Was he a designer?
一位设计师
Was he a filmmaker?
还是电影制作人
But what he was, obviously,
但可以肯定的是
was something
we all wanted to be.
他是那种我们大家都想成为的人
RAY EAMES: I had been trained
as a painter,
我之前是学习绘画的
but when we were working
on furniture,
但当我们制作家俱
and again in film,
以及拍摄电影时
it never seemed like leaving
painting in any way,
却从未感觉与绘画完全脱离了关系
because it was
just anotherform.
因为这只是绘画的另一种形式
WOMAN: She made paintings out of
what she was surrounded by.
她总是以身遭事物为题创作绘画
Everything she touched, she
turned into something magical.
她能将所感所知转变成仿有魔力的作品
MAN: Everything that they did
in design, she saw as
她把他们手头的设计
an extension of her painting.
作为她绘画的一种延展
And everything they did in
design, he saw as an extension
而他将他们的设计
of his architecture.
作为他建筑的衍生
For them, these names like
painter and architect,
对于伊姆斯夫妇来说
画家和建筑师
they weren't job descriptions.
并不是他们工作的准确描述
They were ways of looking
at the world.
而只是看待事物的角度和方式
WOMAN: They were
introducing people
这种角度和方式引导着人们
to look at the world
differently.
用不同的眼光看世界
Life was fun, was work, was fun,
was life.
生活和工作都充满着遐思奇趣
WOMAN: People would say
it was childlike behavior,
也许有人会认为这只是孩子气
butwhat's wrong with that?
但孩子气又有什么不妥呢
The Eameses have put
all this joy back in life.
伊姆斯夫妇让生活乐趣泗溢
You know that modernism,
let's face it,
我们不得不承认时至今日
was getting boring.
现代主义已经越来越无聊了
MAN: Had they just designed
the furniture,
仅靠家俱设计的成就
they'd be in the pantheon.
伊姆斯夫妇就可以扬名立万了
It's the multifaceted nature
of the career
而他们事业上的全面多能
that is extraordinary.
更是让人难以望其项背
They give shape to America's
20th century.
他们的艺术生动反映着二十世纪的美国
MAN: I came from
an architectural office
我在一家建筑事物所工作
where there were individual
tables with a conference room,
那里有各自独立的工作台和一个会议室
and there was carpet
on the floor.
地板上铺着地毯
There were lights.
各处都有灯
We had drafting tables,
and all the equipment
我们有绘图桌以及其它必备器具
that you needed,
et cetera, et cetera.
如此等等 应有尽有
I walk into Eames Office,
但当我走进伊姆斯的工作室
and it was like walking
into a circus.
就好像来到了马戏团
WOMAN: I walked in the door, and
of course I immediately thought,
我进门的一瞬间，理所当然地想
"Got any jobs here?'
这是工作的地方吗
MAN: I'm just totally blown away
by the patina on every surface
我被各种表面上蒙尘附锈的模型惊呆了
of graphics, and there were
models everywhere,
这些模型到处都是
and there was just stuff.
屋子里塞得满满的
I was just overwhelmed.
我感到很震憾
MAN: I saw this incredible
apparition
我看到了这个创造了不可思议影像
of animation stands
的动画摄影台
and photographs
spread out on tables.
以及散落在桌面上的各式照片
Models being lit
for photography,
模型上打着光以便拍摄
a screening room,
有影片放映室
and a wonderful wood shop.
和令人惊叹的木工房
Saltwater tanks.
甚至还有热带鱼缸
WOMAN: There were Eames chairs
with Steinberg drawings on them.
那里摆放着伊姆斯椅子
椅子有索尔・斯坦伯格（著名动画师、插画家）的画
Every kind of visual treat
you can imagine.
你所能想像的视觉享受不所不包
And I thought, "I've come
to work in Disneyland."
当我就想，我要在迪士尼乐园工作了
ASHBY: If you had taken
the roof off of it,
如果把屋顶移开
you would see that place
你能看到这里的空间
changing constantly.
是不断变化着的
So we'd just go around
我们走来走去
and take everything
out of the middle
把屋子中间的东西都搬走
ofthe studio,
to put up a movie set
放上电影布景
to take pictures tomorrow,
and then the next day,
以准备次日的拍摄
拍摄完成后
you'd take out all the movie set
and put the tables all back up,
再把布景移走
把工作台之类的放回来
and everybody's
back at work again.
然后所有人再继续之前的工作
WOMAN: It was very informal.
这里制度相当地宽松
I mean, there wasn't ever
any kind
没存在任何形式的
of routine.
常规
There were no
"regular meetings."
也没有所谓“例会”
WOMAN: Because I did not have
a design degree,
因为我没有任何设计文凭
many of the people
in the Office thought
很多人都认为
I probably shouldn't bethere,
我没有资格在这里工作
but Charles had
a different attitude.
但Charles并不这样想
And he said this to me --
有一次他跟我说
"l can teach you
how to draw.
如果你用心观察和思考
"lf you can think
and you can see,
我就能够指导你怎样去画图
and you can prove that to me,
you can work here."
只要你能证明你做得到
你就有资格在这里工作
[Tune chiming]
FRANCO: For four decades,
901 Washington Boulevard
四十年间
加州威尼斯海滩
in Venice Beach, California,
was one of the most
华盛顿林萌大道901号
creative addresses on Earth.
是世上最富有创造力的地点
Dozens of gifted young designers
这个工作室培养了
cuttheirteeth within the walls
ofthe studio.
几十位才华横溢的青年设计师
But the vision for the Office
came from the top.
但工作室需要来自上层的高瞻远瞩
CHARLES EAMES: We have to have
a place where you can recognize
我们的工作室必须是一个能让你
where you're going
when you start out.
着手工作时
心怀明确目标的地方
FRANCO:
Modern design was born
艺术与工业生产的结合
from the marriage
of art and industry.
使现代主义变得平淡无趣
The Eames Office was born
from the marriage
Eames工作室则诞生于
of Ray Kaiser --
a painter who rarely painted --
一个不怎么画画的画家Ray Kaiser
and Charles Eames --
an architecture school dropout
和一个建筑学院辍学生Charles Eames
的结合
who never got his license.
Charles甚至没有建筑师执照
"Eventually, everything
connects," Charles said.
万物自有关联 Charles说道
Furniture, toys, architecture,
在充满狂野奇想的Eames工作室里
exhibitions, photography,
家俱 玩具 建筑
and film were all connected
陈列 摄影
in the wild, whimsical world
of the Eames Office.
以及电影之间都是有关联的
MAN: Charles and Ray Eames
wanted to bring
Charles和Ray Eames希望能给更多的人
the most magnificent experiences
带来眼睛所能看到的
that you could have
with your eyes
最为壮美无匹的
to the largest number of people.
瑰丽视觉体验
I don'tthinkthere's anything
more important
我认为对艺术家而言
for an artist to want to do.
没有什么比这更重要
FRANCO: It was a career
that defined
他们的职业生涯
what it means to be a designer.
界定了设计师的涵义
And it all began with a chair.
而这一切都从一把椅子开始
MAN: Charles, where did the
classic Eames chair come from?
Eames椅子的灵感从何而来
Did it come to you
in a flash,
是你早晨剃须时
as you were shaving
one morning?
脑海中的一个闪念吗
It sort of came to me
如果非要说闪念的话
in a 30-year flash,
if you want.
这个闪念大概有三十年那么长吧
FRANCO: TIME magazine called it
《时代》杂志曾称其为
"the greatest design
ofthe 20th century."
二十世纪最伟大的设计
But it didn't start out
that way.
但它的开端并非伟大
It began as a failure.
甚至是失败的
Responding to a competition
为参加1940年现代艺术博物馆
at the museum of modern art
in 1940,
举行的设计竞赛
two unknown young architects --
两位籍籍无名的建筑家
Charles Eames and his friend,
Eero Saarinen,
Charles Eames 和他的朋友Eero Saarinen
set out to reinvent
the very idea of the chair.
提出这把椅子的设计理念
MAN: The goal is to create
an inexpensive,
当时的目标是创造出一把经过精心设计
mass-produced chair
which is well designed,
而又经济实惠 能够大批量生产的椅子
and which is molded to the body,
because it doesn't need a lot
椅身不需要多余的装饰
故此可以通过模压成型
of upholstery, which is,
"a," old-fashioned,
因为装饰代表着 a：款式老旧过时
and "b," expensive.
b：价格昂贵
Upholstery is what
Louis XlV did.
家俱上的繁复装饰代表着路易十四式的陈旧暮气
FRANCO: Working at the Cranbrook
Academy of Art near Detroit,
在底特律近郊的克兰布鲁克艺术学院
Eames and Saarinen thought they
could mold
Eames和Saarinen想到一种可以
the new miracle material,
plywood,
通过模具成型的神奇材料 胶合板
into two directions at once
它可以向两个不同方向弯曲
to make a comfortable,
form-fitting shell.
而形成舒适、合体的形状
WOMAN: The critical point
关键问题在于
is where that back
becomes the seat.
椅背的处理
ALBRECHT: The glues aren't good
enough, and the chair splinters,
胶水粘合的效果并不好
椅身容易有裂缝
which means,
when you'd sit on it,
这就意味着你坐上去时
itwould be a little
uncomfortable.
会有些不舒服
So they have to upholster it.
所以必须装上椅套
FRANCO: Despite failing
尽管整块胶合板成型的
at their goal of creating
a single-piece plywood shell,
理念失败了
Charles and Eero
won the competition.
Charles和Saarinen最终还是赢得了竞赛
WOMAN: The irony is that
具有讽刺意味的是
the chairthat
Eames and Saarinen designed,
Charles和Saarinen设计的椅子
they couldn't really
manufacture.
无法真正地加工制造出来
FRANCO: Even with the upholstery
to cover the cracked surface,
尽管可以用椅套掩盖表面的裂缝
no existing machine could
successfully mold the plywood
却不存在可以成功地将胶合板
into the shape of the chair.
塑压成型的机器
MAN: It couldn't be made
因为无法像他们声称的那样
in the way that they claimed
it could be made.
制造出这把椅子
They had designed
the look of it
他们只创造了椅子的外形
without designing
the substance of it.
而无法制造出它的实体
FRANCO: After many unsuccessful
attempts,
经过多次失败的尝试
Eero Saarinen scrapped
the project.
Eero Saarinen放弃了这个项目
But Charles wasn't ready
to give up --
但Charles并没有完全心灰意冷
this time, with a new partner.
这一次 他有了新的搭档
At Cranbrook, he had become
friendly with Ray Kaiser,
在克兰布鲁克 他与Ray Kaiser关系亲近起来
At Cranbrook, he had become
friendly with Ray Kaiser,
在克兰布鲁克 他与Ray Kaiser关系亲近起来
a talented young artist who had
helped with the chair project.
她年轻而极具天赋 协助他完成椅子的设计项目
MARlLYN NEUHART:
I said to Ray one day,
某天我问Ray
"How did you and Charles
get together?'
你和Charles是怎么走到一起的
"Oh! I can't talk about it."
哦 我说不好
I said, "Well, why not?'
我问她 为什么呢
"Well, we just did."
我们就是自然而然地在一起了
DEMETRlOS: They sparked, and
the rest is literally history.
他们之间擦出了火花
之后种种已写进历史
And I think in Ray,
我觉得有了Ray
he really found his complement.
他才真正地完整起来
FRANCO: But there was a problem.
可是问题在于
Charles was already married.
Charles已经结婚了
He had moved up to Cranbrook
from St. Louis
他是和他的太太 Catherine和小女儿Lucia
with his wife, Catherine,
and his young daughter, Lucia.
从圣路易斯搬到克兰布鲁克的
KlRKHAM: The love letters are
Charles's letters to Ray,
现存的情书都是Charles写给Ray的
because the letters that Ray
wrote back to Charles,
由于Charles的已婚状态
Charles destroyed,
because he was married.
Ray的回信都被Charles销毁了
They show Charles madly in love
with her.
这些书信表达了Charles对Ray近乎疯狂的爱
There's no doubt about that.
这是毫无疑问的
He talks about walking past
信中他说起路过
the building
that she used to live in
Ray曾经住过的房子
and looking up at her window,
抬头看向她的窗户
and they are very moving.
让他们内心触动不已
These letters are talking about
这些书信中 谈起他们
a joined future
as artists together.
作为艺术家在一起的共同未来
I think
his decision feels made.
我认为他已下定决心
Ray certainly felt uncomfortable
enough to leave Cranbrook
可以肯定Ray并不愿意离开克兰布鲁克
and go away and think about
远走他乡并对今后
what she was going to do
thereafter.
的选择加以考量
DEMETRlOS: Catherine was
a very impressive person.
Catherine是那种容易给人留下深刻印象的人
Knowing them both, as I did,
同我一样知道他们俩的存在
you can see why
they didn't stay together.
可以想像她后来并没有和Charles在一起
He really thought he had
something to offer the world,
Charles真的认为他能给世界带来不同
and this was going to be
a journey
而这过程将是一场充满未知
with a lot
of unexpectedness.
的伟大旅程
This was a journey that might
not lead to, uh, success.
这旅程的终点或许并不是“成功”
And I think that maybe
at that point in her life,
我认为就此而言 对于Catherine来说
this was not necessarily
这个旅程的终点
the place that Catherine
wanted to go.
并不是她想到达的彼岸
But I think that maybe
in Charles's mind
但我想对Charles来说
that he had wanted a life
where love and work
他梦想拥有的 是爱情与事业
and life and work
were all blended together.
生活与事业 可以紧密地相连
FRANCO: Charles quit his job
at Cranbrook,
Charles辞去了克兰布鲁克的工作
and, in one last letterto Ray,
asked for her hand in marriage.
在给Ray的最后一封信中
向她求了婚
His future with his new bride
他和他新婚妻子的未来
now depended
on making the chairwork.
如今都取决于怎样造出那把椅子
Broke and short on options,
在经济拮据且无路可走的情况下
Charles and Ray
headed from Michigan to L.A.
Charles和Ray从密歇根搬到了洛杉矶
to finish what he had started.
去完成他最初的野望
DEMETRlOS: Part of this journey
to California was
对他们来说这场加州之旅
they were both
going to figure out
的意义一部分在于
how to mass-produce molded
plywood and compound curves --
解决怎样大批量生产模塑胶合板
及其复杂曲线的问题
which sounds very unromantic,
but I think it probably
听上去一点也不浪漫
但我认为
was pretty romantic,
underthe circumstances.
在这种困境之下
也许正好相反
FRANCO: In their two-bedroom
apartment in Westwood Village,
在他们位于西木区只有两间卧室的公寓里
Charles and Ray set up
a makeshift workshop.
Charles和Ray建起一个临时工坊
RAY EAMES: The --
the first to --
当时 第一次
that did the molding,
的模压成品
which was so magic,
真的很神奇
we called it by a magic name.
我们给它起了个充满魔力的名字
So we called it "Kazam!"
我们叫它"Kazam!"
FRANCO: The "Kazam!" machine was
a jury-rigged molding device
制造"Kazam!"的机器是一台临时装配的塑模机
made out of heating coils
and a bicycle pump.
由加热线圈和暖气管加工而成
But in 1942,
with the nation atwar,
但在战时的1942年
raw materials were scarce,
and the "Kazam!" lay silent.
原材料稀缺
"Kazam!"也无人问津
Butwith the setback,
there was also opportunity.
纵然难免遭遇挫折
机会却并非渺茫
The U.S. military
needed better splints.
当时美国军方需要更好使的医用夹板
DEMETRlOS: The standard-issue
splintwas metallic,
由于普通夹板为金属材料制成
and so the vibration of
the two people carrying them
在两人搬运伤员时造成的振动
actually would make
the wound worse.
往往使伤口情况恶化
Theywould actually be
better off
但如果从地下捡根树枝
if you grabbed a stick
off the ground and tied it to it
绑上作为固定 的确会比用金属夹板固定
than with this
amplification.
造成的振动要少得多
So Charles and Ray said,
"Well, you know,
所以Charles和Ray表示
we're experimenting
with molded plywood.
我们既然在塑压胶合板上
反复实验
Why don't we try
and design a new splint?'
为什么不去设计一种新的医用夹板呢
They're trying to make
a three-dimensional curve,
他们试着制造出 有着三维曲面
kind of a bowl, you might say.
可以说有点像碗状的器具
They can't quite do it yet.
开始他们并没有成功地造出来
So they need holes
in the plywood
胶合板上必须有洞
in order to release the tension,
才能释放压力
'cause otherwise
it's going to splinter
否则当你试图弯曲时
where they try to do it.
夹板会开裂
Butworking within
the constraints,
但是这些不利因素
what's nice is that this is
exactly what you need
却成为制造夹板的优势
for a splint, 'cause you need
a place for the bandages to go.
因为夹板需要可以绑绷带的地方
FRANCO: In a rented warehouse
space,
Eames夫妇在租来的仓库里
their team of skilled designers
and craftspeople
集合起经验丰富的设计师和手工工匠
made 150,000 splints.
制造出15万个医用夹板
With peace approaching,
Charles and Ray
随着时间推移
had one thing on their minds --
Charles与Ray考虑着同一件事
即
applying the lessons
of the splints
把从制造医用夹板中获得的经验
to the failed
plywood chairs.
应用到历经失败的胶合板椅中去
Thistime, they wouldn't design
the look of the chairfirst.
这一次 他们将不再从椅子的外形着手
DEMETRlOS: They would never make
that mistake again.
他们不会再犯相同的错误
They would let the design flow
from the learning.
而是将习得的经验运用到设计中去
FRANCO: That meant
knowing who they were serving.
这说明他们会去了解自己的服务对象
In Charles's words,
用Charles的话来说
it was always about being
就是作为一个称职的主人
a good host to their guests.
盛情招待他的客人
CHARLES EAMES: The people we
wanted to serve were varied,
我们的服务对象多种多样
and to begin with we studied
the shape and postures
所以我们从研究人体形状和姿势
of many types --
averages and extremes.
的不同入手
从普通到极端个体
FRANCO: But it was more
than just a search
但这并不仅仅是为了
for the best chair design.
椅子的设计作功课
Itwas the beginning
of the Eames design process,
而是Eames设计流程的开端
a process of learning by doing.
此流程即从经验中学习
CHARLES EAMES: In the design
of any structure,
任何结构体系的设计
it is often the connection
连接方式往往是
that provides the key
to the solution.
解决问题的关键
FRANCO: "Never delegate
understanding," Charles said.
Charles说过 不要固步自封
It would become a hallmark
of Eames design,
这也成了Eames设计的标签
their secret ingredient.
也是他们的独家秘方
MAN: Charles said,
yeah, there's a secret.
Charles说 没错 我们的确有秘方
First you have an idea,
then you discard the idea,
最开始你有了一个创意
发现不行 然后丢弃了它
then you have 50 other ideas
and you discard them,
后来你又有了另外50个创意
再把它们统统丢掉
and then you do several models,
and they don'twork,
你做了好几个模型
发现都行不通
and you throwthem out.
然后再全部放弃
And the secret is work and work
and work and work and work.
所以秘方就是不停地工作工作再工作
FRANCO: The plywood furniture
was good to go in 1946.
胶合板家俱在1946年是完全可行的
Charles said of the furniture,
Charles的看法是
"We wanted to make the best
for the most for the least."
我们要给大众提供最为物美价廉的商品
That sentiment struck a chord
这种观点打动了
with the Herman Miller
furniture company.
Herman Miller家俱公司
Honest and simple
in its use of materials,
它的原材料简单而有诚意
the plywood furniture was also
affordable for the common man.
普通民众也负担得起胶合板家俱的价格
Together, they would become one
of the great success stories
他们的合作将在战后
of the postwar era.
获得伟大的成功
ALBRECHT: Charles and Ray Eames
provide much of the furniture
Charles与Ray Eames也为中上层人士
for a kind of
Upper-middle-class,
设计了不少家俱
educated audience
接受过良好教育的人们
moving to suburbia.
搬到了郊区
When the Second World War ended,
二战结束以后
itwasn't just five years
of pent-up demand.
所要满足的不仅仅是战时五年间被压抑的需求
Itwas actually almost 15 years,
而是近乎十五年
because you also have 10 years
of the Depression.
因为之前美国还经历了十年的经济萧条
And people have much more money,
当人们手头宽裕时
so if you wanted to sort of
do something
如果想要买点什么
differentthan your parents,
you boughtthat Eamesfurniture.
不同于父母辈的东西
就会选择Eames家俱
And itwas promoted that way.
每家公司的营销策略
Everything around the marketing
suggested,
都怂恿着大众
"Here is something new
for a new society."
新社会要用时髦商品
And America was a new society
in '45.
而四十年代中期 美国正是处于一个新的社会
FRANCO: In the decades
to follow,
在接下来的几十年中
Charles and Ray scored success
Charles和Ray设计出一个又一个系列的
with line after line
of Eames furniture.
Eames家俱 都取得了成功
And their unmistakable designs
他们永不出错的设计
became a ubiquitous part
of American culture,
成为了美国文化中无处不在一的部分
right up to today.
直至今日
Sold for $900, 232.
900232美元成交
I think the work retains
a real freshness.
我认为这些设计永不过时
Elements of it still inform
contemporary design today.
其中一些元素仍旧影响着当代设计
AUCTlONEER: $700.
700美元
AUCTlONEER: $2,000.
2000美元
$2, 100.
2100美元
AUCTlONEER: $2, 100.
AUCTlONEER: $7,000.
7000美元
AUCTlONEER: Fair warning,
selling...$13,000.
提醒大家
13000美元
Are we done?
还有人出价吗
Sold for $13,000.
13000美元成交
WRlGHT: The rightness
of thefurniture
Eames家俱的出众之处
will continue to appeal
持续影响着
to new generations.
好几代人
MAN: The word "Eames" has now
become a generic word.
"Eames" 已成为人们耳熟能详的通用词
I mean, if you go on eBay,
it always says, "Eames era"
如果你登录eBay
会看到"Eames era"这样的标签
blah, blah, blah.
如此等等
So it's become
a word like "Victorian."
可与"Victorian"（维多利亚时代风）相提并论
Maybe it's, in a way, accurate,
没准还真是挺贴切的
because just like Queen Victoria
因为就如同维多利亚女王
represents an attitude,
Eames家俱同样代表了一种态度（好想翻成“逼格”）
Eames also embodies
a certain approach
Eames也象征着生活与思考
to life and to thinking.
的一种方法和途径
FRANCO: By the early '50s,
Charles had grown
五十年代早期
Charles显赫的声誉
an outsized reputation
as an icon of modernism,
已使其成为现代主义的标杆
fighting to inject
an ethical dimension
与把伦理道德强行注入
into American capitalism.
美国资本主义市场的观念作斗争
At that price,
the customer knows
这种价格之下
顾客能够
exactly what
he's going to get.
清楚知道
他购得的商品是怎样的
This!
像这样
FRANCO: In MGM's
"Executive Suite,"
米高梅拍摄制作的Executive Suite（中译《纵横天下》）中
William Holden stars
William Holden扮演的
as a curiously
Charles Eames-like
Charles Eames式的
furniture designer.
家俱设计师
We'll have a line
of low-priced furniture,
我们将要推出一系列平价家俱
a new and different line,
那将是全新 而与以往截然不同的系列
as differentfrom anything
we're making today
不同于如今我们制造的所有商品
as a modern automobile is
different from a covered wagon.
就好像汽车不同于马车
FRANCO: In the outside world,
Charles's reputation
Charles的声名在外部世界里
may have grown larger than life,
也许令人难以望其项背
butwithin the Eames Office,
但在Eames工作室中
there was always the lingering
question of credit.
荣誉归属问题总是徘徊不去
SUSSMAN: There are still
some sore issues
那里存在着一些令人不快的症结
among certain people who feel
they never were recognized
有一部分人认为他们从未得到
as much as they should,
应得的认可
but it's a very delicate issue.
其性质也颇为敏感微妙
FRANCO: The issue came to a head
back in 1946
问题的根源 需要回溯至1946年
atthe unveiling
of the original Eames chair
初版Eames椅首次公开亮相时
when the museum of modern art
gave Charles a one-man show.
现代艺术博物馆为Charles举办单人秀
ALBRECHT: MOMA gives the name
Charles Eames,
现代艺术博物馆以Charles Eames为活动冠名
and this causes a certain
tension in the Office,
导致了工作室相当紧张的内部氛围
because it was thought to be
a collaborative effort.
因为很多人认为椅子的成功是大家通力合作的结果
MAN: It's not that he's swooping
in or is doing nothing
倒不是说他什么都没做空手套白狼
and scarfing up all the credit,
还把名誉据为己有
but he is not the only designer
that was involved.
但他并不是唯一参与的设计师
SUSSMAN: This happens
all the time.
事情总是这样
Agroup of young people
co-creating
一群年轻人一起工作
and influencing each other
and inspiring each other,
互相影响
互相激发
and then the question is,
"Who did what?'
然而问题在于
功劳怎样分配
One of the last projects
在最后的项目中
I worked on was
"Day of the Dead," the film.
我参与 Day of the Dead （《亡灵节》）的拍摄
I was down in Mexico
helping with thatfilm,
南下墨西哥协助电影制作
shooting, gathering objects,
摄影 收集素材
and setting the type.
设置胶片
And I wrote,
"Assistance in Mexico,"
然后我写下了
墨西哥协助人员
and I wrote the names
ofthe people.
把参与拍摄的人名都写了下来
So Charles came by my desk
and said, "What is that?!"
Charles经过我的桌前问
你这是干嘛
And I said, "But we worked
on it, didn't we?'
我回答
我们都有份参与的，没错吧
ASHBY: I went to New York
many, many times,
我为了time-life大厦大堂的工作
putting the time life
lobbies together,
往纽约跑过很多次
（指Eames工作室为time-life大厦大堂设计的椅子和高脚凳）
and Charles never went
and saw them
在这项工作期间
（Time-Life Chair and Stool的主要设计者应为受雇于工作室的Peter Jon Pearce）
while the things
were being constructed,
Charles从没到场看过一眼
but I could never say
我无法声称
that I designed anything
at the Eames Office.
我在Eames工作室有任何作品
I never saw anything
come out of there that was not
我所见每一样工作室出来的东西
signatured, you know,
by him and Ray.
都打着他和Ray的标签
OPPEWALL: When a product
comes out,
每件产品的诞生
it's a river.
都好比一条河流
It starts at one point,
有其发源地
and it ends at another point.
亦有其终结点
Many people jump into it
along the way.
很多人都是半道跳下来的
BEEBE: And everybody contributes
a small piece,
每个人都作出过其贡献
but only if they go on
after that
但只有大家一起努力
to produce
a stunning amount ofwork,
才能成就惊世之作
I think, are they
capable of saying,
我想
他们是否能声称
"l did this, this, and this
我在Eames工作室
in the Eames Office
with no credit."
做了这个 这个 和这个
却没有任何名分
WOMAN: I think he ran the Office
a bit like a Renaissance studio.
我觉得他经营这个工作室的方式
有点像文艺复兴时期的画家工作室
You know, there's
a master painter,
首先要有一个绘画大师
butthen there are
all the other people
然后就是其他的助手
who help realize the work.
以协助作品的实现
OPPEWALL: He may have been
exploiting us,
也许他曾经利用过我们
but if you were not stupid,
但你要是不傻的话
you were also exploiting
that relationship.
你总是会在这种雇佣关系里利用他人的
I was happy,
我还挺高兴
being exploited
被一个真正的大师
by a proper master.
剥削的
MAN: The most
wonderful work is --
一个充满良知和才华的作者
is the conscience
and the talents of a person
有权将他的名字
who have every right
to have their name on it,
署在最棒的作品上
even though it's done
by minions of other people.
哪怕创作的过程中
占有了他人的劳动成果
Things good and bad,
不论好坏
he rightfully has his name
on them, and they rightfully
他都有权在作品上署名
而这些作品都
are Charles Eames or
Charles and Ray Eames products.
理所应当地被Charles Eames或
Charles和Ray Eames署名
ARLENE FRANClS: Almost always,
when there's a successful man,
自古以来
一个成功的男人
ARLENE FRANClS: Almost always,
when there's a successful man,
自古以来
一个成功的男人
there is a very interesting
and able woman behind him.
背后都有一个非常有趣能干的女人
And a better case
could seldom befound
很少有和Charles与Ray
than in Ray and Charles Eames.
相比更加成功的例子了
Come on in, Ray.
上来吧，Ray
Hello,
I'm so happy to see you.
你好
非常高兴见到你
This is Mrs. Eames,
and she's going to tell us
这位是Eames太太
她会告诉我们
how she helps Charles
design these chairs.
她是怎样帮助Charles
设计那些椅子的
How do you manage that?
你是怎么做到的
Well, uh, aside from serving
呃 除了在测试中
as an extreme in the testing,
贡献些极端案例之外
there are a million things,
还有很多其他事物
but, uh, I think
the most difficult thing
不过 嗯 我觉得最为困难的
is to keep the big idea,
是在创造中保持
to be able to look
critically at the work.
具有批判性的远见
ALBRECHT: Arlene Francis is
clearly having a hard time
Arlene Francis和这对夫妇一起工作时
with this husband and wife
working together.
显然过得并不轻松
You know, this is the era
of "Mad Men,"
在如今看来
as we're watching now.
那是一个狂人时代
This is not fitting.
最开始进展并不顺利
And Charles Eames is trying
to promote Ray Eames,
Charles Eames曾努力使Ray Eames
得到提高
as saying that,
"We collaborated on this."
他对她说 我们要互相合作
CHARLES EAMES: Well, uh, Ray --
Ray was a painter.
嗯 Ray之前是个画家
Ray worked here in New York with
Hans Hofmann for a long time,
她曾在纽约和Hans Hofmann（德裔抽象表现主义艺术家）
一起工作了很长时间
which is a pretty good start.
这对她来说是个不错的开端
KlRKHAM: I actually thought
Charles was more embarrassed
我认为当时相比Ray
than Ray.
Charles处在一个更尴尬的境地
Ray is hidden away.
Ray可以躲在幕后
Charles is being highlighted,
the great male designer.
Charles却作为伟大的男性设计师
暴露在聚光灯下
It's a very interesting moment
1950年代 性别政治下的美国
of American sexual politics
in the 1950s.
正处在一个颇为微妙的时期
Uh, I wonder if you're going
to maybe take us through
我想请你来给大家说说
and show how -- how the Eames
chair has developed.
向我们展示一下Eames椅的诞生过程
And, Ray, shall we
let Charles do it,
Ray 你说我们是让Charles来说呢
or do you want
to help with it?
还是由你来帮他
Please, please.
拜托了 别这样
No, you see, as I told you,
she is behind the man,
不想说吗 你们看 我说得没错吧
她是这个男人背后的贤内助
but terribly important.
但是至关重要
Thank you, Ray.
All right, Charles --
谢谢你了 Ray
好吧 Charles
SUSSMAN: The feminist conscience
had not been yet raised.
女权主义意识尚未兴起
Ray would always stand
behind Charles.
Ray总是躲在Charles背后
And on camera or in interviews,
she said hardly anything.
在镜头前 访谈中
她几乎不怎么说话
EDWARD P. MORGAN: Her warm
but quiet conversation
她人很亲切
但拙于言辞
shrank to total silence
before the camera,
在镜头前几乎完保持沉默
but her impact on Eames' work
spoke for her.
但她对Eames作品的影响
不言而喻
She sat like a delicious
dumpling in a doll's dress,
她就好像一只美味的
穿着洋娃娃装的水果布丁一样坐在那里
concentrating
on a sweep of subjects
专注于掠过多得几乎能
which would seemingly
choke a computer.
把电脑弄死机的话题
ASHBY: People always made
the mistake
人们总是会把
that Charles and Ray,
it was two brothers.
Charles和Ray误认为是两兄弟
They were a married couple,
他们是一对夫妇
while at the same time,
they were partners
同时也是创作出他们
in whatever
their design effort was.
共同设计成果的搭挡
OPPEWALL: Ray felt, I think,
我想偶尔Ray会感到
deeply enraged
and hurt, on occasion,
愤怒和受伤害
when it was assumed that it was
因为他们共同的事业
actually just Charles's business
被看作只是Charles的
and it was the office
of Charles Eames,
工作室也只是Charles的
not the office
of Charles and Ray Eames.
而不是Charles与Ray Eames工作室
It was Charles
who was in charge,
Charles掌控一切
but the body of work
would not have been the same
但如果没有Ray的贡献
without Ray's contributions,
他们的作品不会是如今这般模样
and how you separate that out,
I don't know.
我不知道
怎么可以抹杀Ray的努力
FRANCO: If the public saw Ray
as little more
如果公众只是把Ray看作
than the devoted wife
supporting her husband,
一个甘于奉献自己支持丈夫事业的妻子
Charles saw a talented artist
who had participated
Charles却把她看作一个参与
in the birth of abstract art
in America.
美国抽象艺术肇始的艺术家
Her mentor was the German
abstract expressionist
她的导师是德裔抽象表现艺术家
Hans Hofmann.
Hans Hofmann
PERL: Hofmann is one
of the great catalytic figures
Hofmann是启发了美国现代艺术
in American art.
的伟大人物之一
He starts a school
in New York City in '33
他1933年在纽约创办的学校
with at times no more than
a dozen or two students.
当时只有十几二十个学生
They, together, are the seed
out of which
Ray和Hofmann一同引导了
the new American art
really grows.
美国新型艺术的兴起
He was getting ideas from people
Hofmann从蒙德里安、保罗・克利、康定斯基
Iike Mondrian, Paul Klee,
Kandinsky,
等人的作品中获得灵感
but he was communicating them
但并非当作教科书一样
not as textbook learning, but as
this incredibly visceral
生搬硬套
而是总其内在的
sensation.
菁华
And I have talked to people
who remember him
我曾与还记得他的人们交谈过
walking into the studio and
looking at a drawing of theirs
说起Hofmann如何走进画室
看着他们手头的画作
and tearing it down the middle
把画纸从中间撕开
and then taking the two parts
and moving them.
然后把撕开的画错位
And then suddenly something
that had been very static
让人觉得原本凝滞的画面
was dynamic.
顿时充满生气
KlRKHAM: So I think it's there
that Ray learned
我认为Ray从那里学到了一些…
some, at least, of this
wonderful capacity that she had
至少是用拼贴、并置手法
for collaging,
for juxtaposition.
处理画面的神奇能力
She could move things around
very, very easily
她能够轻易地移动创作对象
and beautifully and find form,
使其组合更加美观
并轻松地找到恰当的形式
and find form
in relation to other form.
并找到与其他形式的关联
SUSSMAN: Ray knew what was art
Ray懂得什么才是艺术
and what was not.
而哪些完全不是
And Charles depended
on her aesthetic genius.
Charles则依赖于她的美学天赋
OPPEWALL: And she would put
objects on shoots
她能够在拍摄创作对象时
that would just bring
the whole thing to life.
将生命力注入其中
By putting the stack
of black wire chairs
她把放作一堆的黑色钢丝椅
naked with the wooden bird
和一只有着小小金属腿的
with the little wire legs,
木制鸟儿放在一起
gave you a very different
feeling about those chairs.
让椅子的形式令人耳目一新
ASHBY: Charles could not deal
with the idea
Charles无法应对
that any of the furniture
would have color on it.
家俱上有任何色彩的想法
If you put a palette of colors
in front of him,
如果你把整个调色板放到他面前
they just-- like he couldn't
handle it.
那就…他根本不知从何下手
It just went
over his head.
根本不在他的考虑范围里
He deferred to her completely
on color sense.
在色彩的应用上他依赖于Ray
BEEBE: She saw everything
as a painting.
她把一切都从绘画的角度审视
She had these enormous eyes
that were --
她有着永远保持觉醒的
they were open like this
all the time.
极其精准的眼光
And I think Charles
was very dependent on that.
这方面Charles总是依靠着她
SUSSMAN: You could just
hear him say,
你总是能听到他喊
"Ra-ay!"
Ra-ay!
Which meant, "Come and help!"
言下之意就是 快来帮我
FRANCO: At the Library
of Congress,
在美国国会图书馆
Ray's letters
to a traveling Charles
我们可以看到Ray写给旅行中Charles的书信中
show herfastidious attention
to every detail
表达了她对他们的生活和事业中
of their life and work.
每个微小细节都极其挑剔
MAN: When she writes to Charles
in Paris
她给人在巴黎的Charles的信中
and she's talking about
the slides that he's just taken,
谈起关于Charles拍下的照片
and she has this sketch
showing how she
把她与Sandro和Don Albinson对
and Sandro and Don Albinson
have changed the chair.
椅子设计的修改画成草图
And then she's going on
about thefilms,
还说起制作电影
and she's going on
about Elmer Bernstein.
以及Elmer Bernstein（演员）
Then she tells him all
the places to shop in Paris
她告诉Charles在巴黎购物的好去处
and where to get his shoes
以及上哪儿买鞋子
and where to get her gloves
上哪儿买她的手套
and whatthe stitching
should be like on the gloves
手套上的应该有怎样的针脚
and howthis perfume
by Balmain is $55 an ounce here,
巴尔曼香水在美国要55美元一盎司
but it's cheaper in Paris,
"and please get it for me."
而在巴黎买要更便宜
拜托帮我买一些
SELlGSOHN: It's as if
they were one individual
就像他俩是处于两具躯体
with two different
special areas,
中的同一个人
and a lot of it was unspoken,
而很多东西无需言传
just eye -- eye contact.
一切尽在眼神的接触
A nodding of something --
an idea
只要轻轻一点头
thatthey both would agree on.
就能达成共识
PEATROSS: So that's how
you begin to separate
你如何能区分他们
their artistic personalities
and their contributions.
的艺术家性情和对艺术的贡献
Butthe separating them
isn't the important part.
但区分他们并不重要
It's what they created together.
重要的是他们的联手创造
That's why it's so good.
这就是他们的作品这么好的原因
FRANCO: Perhaps the greatest
Eames design of all
也许最棒的Eames设计
was the image
of Charles and Ray.
就是Charles与Ray的公众形象
Their playful self-portraits,
eccentric dress,
他们妙趣横生的照片
离经叛道的服装
and quotable quotes
all contributed
说过的引句名言
都勾画出了
to the endearing picture
of a happy, modern couple
一对专注于攀登事业高峰的
absorbed in the challenges
of their work.
幸福现代爱侣的图景
Charles and Ray
were cultural icons,
Charles和Ray是文化标签
buttheir public face masked
a deep desire for privacy.
但他们用对隐私的渴求
保护着他们的公众形象
After long hours at 901,
在901号生活多年以后
they would retreat
to the home they built
他们搬到了位于Pacific Palisades
in Pacific Palisades.
自己建造的家中
SUSSMAN: Charles and Ray were
their own community,
Charles和Ray就是一个紧密的小团体
and we were
in the satellite group.
而我们像卫星一样围着他们转
And so was everybody else.
其他人也是一样
ASHBY: I had no sense that they
were trying to keep out
他们把外面世界和其他无关
the outside world
or anything else.
的事物都排除在外
They had created a world
and a lifestyle
他们创造了自己的世界和生活方式
thatjust required them to go
这种生活方式让他们
in this tunnel from their house
在自己的家和工作场所之间
to the work, you know,
back home again,
形成了一个隧道
sowhat you surround yourself
with and the choices you make
故此他们身边事物和所选择的
about where you live
and how you live
生活场所、方式
and the artifacts you have,
以及手工制品
they're all based upon
trying to create
全都基于他们创造的
a seamless environment
and a seamless life.
封闭的生活环境
FRANCO: Originally, the house
was designed by Charles
他们房子的设计原本是来自
with Eero Saarinen as part of
1945年Charles和Eero Saarinen参与的
the influential case study
housing program in 1945.
著名住房建设规划研究项目
But Charles and Ray were not
ones to let a good design rest.
Charles和Ray没有让这个项目就此闲置
DEMETRlOS: Charles Eames and
Eero Saarinen designed a house
我们知道Charles Eames和Eero Saarinen
that we now call
the Bridge House,
设计的房子现在叫桥屋
and it was forthis site.
是为此处地点度身定制的
It would have cantilevered
from the hillside
从山腰上支起悬架
out into the middle
of the meadow.
置身于草地之中
One of the ideas of the house
was to use technologies
桥屋的创作理念之一
that had come
out of the war effort.
来自于战时技术
So all the parts of this house
所以房子的每一个部分
were off the shelf.
都是现货拼装
FRANCO: But the Bridge House
was never built.
但桥屋从未真正搭建出来
DEMETRlOS: After World War ll,
二战结束之后
there were major
material shortages,
国内物资紧缺
and it took about
two or three years
甚至花了两三年时间
to even get the parts
thatthey had ordered.
他们才收到订货
And in that time,
Charles and Ray
那时Charles和Ray
fell in love with this meadow.
爱上了这片草地
RAY EAMES: We spent all --
all our spare time here.
我们把所有的闲暇时间都花在这里了
Began to think itwould be
criminal to put that house
觉得把一栋房子建在
in the middle
ofthe field.
这片草地中间是一种罪过
WOMAN: Charles realized,
Charles意识到
"Oh, we're making the classic
architect's mistake."
我们犯了一个建筑师的经典错误
You find
a beautiful site,
你发现一个美丽的地方
and you plunk a house
in the middle of it.
然后就把一栋房子杵在中央
FRANCO:
With the meadow in mind,
心里记挂着那片草地
Charles and Ray redesigned
the Bridge House
Charles和Ray重新设计了桥屋
and began construction.
并开始建造
MAN: It was relatively quick,
有赖于某些形式的预制件
because they were relying on
some form of prefabrication,
他们的速度还是比较快的
of bringing materials
to the site
因为一旦把预制件带到工地
and assembling them.
只要组装起来就行
FRANCO: On Christmas Eve, 1949,
1949年圣诞前日
Charles and Ray moved in.
Charles和Ray搬了进来
Hines: The Eames house
in Los Angeles
Eames宅位于洛杉矶
on that bluff
overlooking the Pacific Ocean
俯瞰太平洋
is surely one of the great
buildings ofthe 20th century.
无愧为二十世纪最伟大的建筑之一
FRANCO: Known to architectural
historians
建筑史学家眼里的
as Case Study House Number 8,
八号案例研究所（Case Study House Number 8）
[即Eames宅]
it is the archetypal
modern house.
是现代房屋的原型
Or at least,
it started that way.
或者说
至少他们最开始是这样设计的
WRlGHT: The Eames house
as it was first made
Eames宅建造初期
is very different
from what it became
与夫妇俩居住多年的
as they lived in it
through the years
最后成品有很大不同
and as it acquired
all their little touches.
其中有着Eamse夫妇相当多的个人印记
I think people miss that
我想如果不是置身其中
unless you've really been there
and been inside of it.
人们甚至会忽略这一点
Now, do you remember this?
你还记得这个吗
Do you remember this?
I do.
我记得
Uh, I don't remember
this one here,
我倒是不记得放在这里的
but there was at least one
at the Office.
不过至少我在工作室见过这个
[Playing tune]
MAN: Modern design has this
sort of clich?of being
某些陈旧观念中
超级大反派的房子
the, you know,
the homes of super villains.
就是这种现代设计风格
Very hard-edged things.
有着非常酷炫的摆设
You can't have, you know,
your Pepperidge Farm cookies
你不能把非凡农庄牌的饼干
on the kitchen counter,
because that's going to ruin,
就这么直接搁在厨房流理台上
因为会毁掉
you know,
this perfecttableau
那幅代表着你完美生活的
of this perfect life
that you live.
完美室内场景
But you would never look
但当你看着Eames宅
at the Eames House
and think that.
就绝不会有那种想法了
The container for your life
can be simple,
你住的房子也许是简约风
but that doesn't mean
your life has to be simple.
但你的生活没必要过个简单无趣
SUSSMAN: What was in the house
was a combination of things
这所房子里有着你完全没见过
that one hadn't seen before.
的事物的大集合
There was a tumbleweed
hanging from the ceiling.
天花板悬挂着风滚草
Well, now you can see a lot of
tumbleweed around
如今你在很多人家里都可以看到风滚草
in people's houses,
but in those days,
可以看到风滚草
但是在那个年代
itwas [Gasps].
那真是让人吃惊
And nearthe tumbleweed
hanging from the ceiling,
而且在风滚草的旁边
there were two
Hans Hofmann paintings
两幅Hans Hofmann的绘画
suspended from
the deck of the roof.
从天花板上悬于半空中
The floorwas just another
canvas for Ray,
地板也是Ray的画布
the ceiling was
just another canvas,
天花板亦然
a sofa was a canvas
for a collage of objects.
沙发也呈现着拼贴画作的美感
She would have entirely
all of her famous
家中放置着层层叠起的
blue and white dishes
stacked up.
Ray著名的蓝白餐具
But she would have little red
hearts or little red accents.
但她会匠心点缀以一些红色
And it was all perfect.
使一切看起来如此完美
MAN: I went to dinner
有一天晚上我去Ray和Charles家吃饭
at Ray and Charles's house
one night,
我去Ray和Charles家吃饭
and it came to dessert.
到了上甜点的时候
So what they had arranged
for dessert
他们上的甜点
was three bowls of flowers
是把三个盛着鲜花的碗
thatthey put in front of you
摆在你面前
to admire,
so it was a visual dessert.
让你去欣赏
所以算是视觉甜点
I was really [bleep] off
with that,
跟你们说
I can tell you.
我当时可生气了
I was really --
because I hadn't eaten much.
我真的…
因为我本来就没吃饱
I was saving up for the --
so I'm looking
我留着肚子准备…
我当时就看着
atthese stupid flowers,
you know,
那些愚蠢的花说道
and I'm saying, "What the hell
is wrong with these people?'
这些人他妈有什么毛病
You know, so I got in my car,
所以我上了自己的车
and I drove out to the nearest
Dairy Queen.
开去了当时离我最近的冰雪皇后冷饮店
FRANCO: "Take your pleasure
seriously," Charles said,
Charles曾说过
认真对待你的赏心乐事
and that's exactly
whatthey did.
他夫妇俩也正是这么做的
[Circus music playing]
OPPEWALL: Every time
每一次
the Ringling Brothers
and Barnum & Bailey Circus
林林兄弟和巴纳姆与贝利马戏团
would come to town, we would all
get out our cameras
来到城里
我们都会拿起照相机
and our ectochrome, and we'd go
和胶卷
跑到商业区
running downtown, and we'd
photograph the circus.
给马戏团拍摄照片
MAN: And he said, "Photograph."
Charles说 照片
"What?'
什么
He said, "Anything you want.
Just photograph."
他说 你要做的就是只拍照片
And a couple of people
of the audience
而有几个人坐在观众席里
were there to feed you.
为你提供所需
It's like a machine gun,
好像机枪一样
somebody was feeding you
the cartridges.
旁边有人给你递子弹/胶卷（cartridge亦作：胶卷）
And I took a lot of pictures.
就这样我拍了不少照片
MAN: What impressed him was
how everybody knew their place,
他很高兴地看到每个人各司其职
and sometimes they had
他们往往
two or three different tasks
thatthey had to do.
手里有两到三种各自的任务要完成
CAPLAN: The circus looks
like a free-for-all
马戏团就像一场自由竞技
and is absolutely
a model of constraints.
是一种实实在在的带着锁链的舞蹈
OPPEWALL: And for Charles,
this was one supreme example --
对于Charles来说是“表演”
"the performance."
的极好例证
"Never let the blood show,"
he would say.
他会说 绝不见血
And this went back
to his philosophy
这就可以回到Charles的设计哲学
of no good design,
no good performance
不论是好的设计
还是好的表演
without restrictions, without
restraints, without rules.
都离不开束缚 克制 和规则
ASHBY: He goes to the circus,
and he just
他来到马戏团
is overwhelmed by the
被其中每样事物的丰富和精彩
of everything, you know,
而震撼不已
the costumes and the wagons
戏服啦 马车啦
and the tent.
还有帐篷
And he comes back,
and he's trying to --
当他回到家
他试图…
you can't turn a circus
into a piece of furniture,
因为你没法把马戏团变成家俱
but he's desperately wanting to.
但是他非常想这么做
FRANCO: Charles and Ray did not
turn the circus into a chair,
Charles和Ray并没有把马戏团做成椅子
butthey did turn
the Eames Office into a circus.
但他们确实把Eames工作室变成了马戏团
[Drum roll]
[March playing]
ASHBY: He wasn't
embarrassed at all
他从不为他做的这些事
about what it is
that he was doing.
感到尴尬
You know, he felt really
confident about,
他对此很自信
"Yeah, this is a toy shop.
没错 这就是个玩具店
This -- I'm just
having fun here.
我玩得非常开心
And, you know, somehow or other,
you guys bring me money
如此这般
你们给我点钱
and tell me to go ahead,
and I'm going to."
告诉我 去玩吧
然后我就开心地去了
FRANCO: Royalties from
Herman Miller gave Charles
Herman Miller米勒公司付给Charles的版权税
the freedom to move beyond
his reputation
使他有自由可以超越自己
as a designer
of modern furniture.
作为现代家俱设计师身份
SCHRADER: Herman Miller
was always after him
Herman Miller总是催着他
to do more chairs, and he would
do chairs every now and then,
设计更多椅子
他也时不时地会做一些
but I don't think he liked
to think of himself
但我认为他并不愿意让自己
or have others think of him
或他们只把他当作
as the chair designer.
一个设计椅子的
[Trumpet playing]
SCHRADER: I was a film critic,
我曾是个影评人
and that gave me an excuse
to go down to 901.
这就给了我去901号的理由
I fell in love with
the whole concept of 901,
我爱上了901的整体概念
which was a kind of
他们在901做的各种事
Renaissance art workshop,
where they did everything.
就好像某种
文艺复兴时期艺术作坊的重现
At the time, he was considered
当时有些人认为Charles
a kind of cutesy,
pass?little filmmaker,
是个有些矫揉造作的电影制作人
but no one had ever written
about the films.
但从来没有人写下过关于那些电影的只言片语
FRANCO: Eames films
are their own genre,
Eames电影有着他们的个人风格
the product not of a film studio
concerned with profits,
他们并不像一般电影制片厂一样追求赢利
but of a curious mind
yearning to communicate
而是一个充满好奇心的头脑切盼着
the complex beauty
of everyday objects.
将每一天所看到的繁杂又美好事物联系起来
[Jazz playing]
CHARLES EAMES: We've never used
film as an art form.
我们从不把电影看作艺术形式
We just use film as a tool.
而是将其看作一种工具
[Mariachi music playing]
SCHRADER: They were, at heart,
他们打从心里就
a kind of mixture of vanity
and self-expression.
混杂着自负和艺术上的个性表现
They only had one obligation,
and thatwas
他们只有一项义务
to satisfy Charles.
即 使Charles满意
CHARLES EAMES:
Much of our energy
我们的精力很大程度就像
is like the guy in Vaudeville
that has
就像杂技团的演员
the plates going, and he's
试图一次同时
intent on getting 30 plates
spinning at one time,
让三十个盘子转起来
but part of the process is
而在这此过程中
quickly being aware of the ones
that are winding down,
要做的是让那些慢下来的盘子
and keeping them spinning.
继续转起来
ASHBY: One of the titles
that began to circulate
一个头衔开始在工作室的雇员中流传
between all the employees
的雇员中流传
was the Eamery,
because it was like this place
Eamery
因为很大程度上工作室的
where everyone was driven
to work all the time.
每一个人都被驱使着全天候地工作
SUSSMAN: It was 24/7,
每周七天
每天二十四小时
365.
年年如此
JOHN NEUHART: Going
to the Eames Office
来到Eames工作室
and watching people
at their desks
看着人们坐在桌前
was like watching people
take their brains out
觉得他们简直殚精竭虑
and knead them like dough.
绞尽脑汁
People that came
from the outside
外来的访客
couldn't believe that this was
the way things were done,
几乎无法相信这就是他们的工作方式
but itwas a delicious agony.
但这的确是痛并快乐着
Itwas like a temple for me.
这里就像是苦修的殿堂
OPPEWALL: Many of us
understood very well
我们中的很多人都深深地懂得
thatwe were very poorly suited
for employment
自己并不适合受雇于
in certain kinds of jobs.
某种特定的职业
We were very well suited
to be thete.
但我们非常适合在这里工作
ASHBY: Charles had a terrible
time interacting with people.
Charles与他人交往往往导致不快
Several times, I hired people,
有好几回
我雇了些人
and they would be there
like three days,
他们来这也就三天吧
and he'd come to me and say,
"l just can't stand that guy.
Charles就跑来跟我说
我受不了那个人了
Get him out of here."
炒了他吧
And I never did know what it was
我从来不明白他
that he saw in that person
到底看人家哪里不顺眼
that he could just not
work with them.
就是没法和人家一起工作
ROCHE: I happen to have
a sort of interest in language
有次我偶然地对于语言
as a means of communication,
which I like to believe
在交流中的意义产生了兴趣
我相信交流
can be simple and direct.
可以是简单而直接的
Charles, I would say,
didn't subscribetothat.
但我得说Charles却并不是这么认为的
Uh, no, we have to -- you know,
the only thing is, uh, Perry,
呃  不  我们得  你知道  重点在于  嗯  Perry
we have to have some sort of
a background before we do this,
我们在着手工作之前得了解一些背景
because one sort of begins to --
因为我们开始时要…
SUSSMAN: His speech wasn't
yadda, yadda, yadda, yadda.
他的表达并不是很流畅
It was stop and go,
and stop and go.
总是说说停停结结巴巴
No, you -- you let me -- cut
this, let me re-- let me --
不 你 你得让我 别拍了 让我 呃 让我
ROCHE: He had
this incredible ability
他有那种把每个话题
to surround every subject
都表达得含糊不清的能力
with a little cloud ofwords.
简直不可思议
We -- we were hoping to --
我们  我们希望
there were two --
there were several things.
那里有两
那里有些事
There was, uh...
那里  呃
ROCHE: You finally
got the message
你得花上十五到二十分钟
at the end of about
15 or 20 minutes of wondering,
才能明白他要表达什么
"Whatthe hell is he
talking about?'
他到底在他妈说啥啊
It finally dawned on you
that he was telling you
你终于领会到他要告诉你
you were an absolute clown
你真是个可笑的小丑
becausethere's something wrong.
因为有些事被你搞错了
CHARLES EAMES: This one is
going to have something to do
接下来我要说的
with what I think of
as the new covetables.
和我最近的兴趣点有些关系
JOHN NEUHART: He appeared
one day at a conference at UCLA,
有次他来到加利福尼亚大学洛杉矶分校的大会上
and he started to speak, and it
just ran right off the track.
开始演讲
说着说着就离题了
Looked up, and he said,
"I'm sorry.
他抬起头说
很抱歉
I just --
isn't going to work today."
我只是 今天不在状态
And somebody said, "No, no!"
然后有人冲他喊
别啊
So he said,
"Well, give me a minute."
他说
好吧 等我一分钟
He put his head down.
他低下头
And everybody waited.
大家都等着
And it took about two minutes.
过了两分钟后
And he raised up.
他把头抬起来
And he just took off.
Boom.
Boom 演讲成功了
CHARLES EAMES: Reams of paper.
一令一令的纸
（一令纸为500张）
What you do with a ream of paper
当你使用一令纸时
can never quite come up
to what the paper offers.
你绝对没有对它物尽其用
[Cheers and applause]
JOHN NEUHART: He knew
where his center was.
他清楚他的心之所向
And there are not a lot of
people that can do that.
这并不是人人都能做到的
I -- I have buttons
that get pushed,
我有被驱使前进的动力
but I don't know
where my center is.
但我并不知道毕生应专注何处
FRANCO: For Charles,
knowing where his center was
对Charles而言 心之所向意味着
meant working
for powerful clients
在服务于强大有权力的客户时
without compromising his ideals.
不在创意上妥协
And making a film to represent
the United States
在1959年共产主义下的苏俄拍摄
in communist Russia in 1959
反映美国的电影
would put that philosophy
to the test.
是对他创作哲学的考验
ALBRECHT: At the height
of the Cold War,
冷战时期
the American government
美国政府
and the government
of the Soviet Union
与苏联政府
decided to hold
joint expositions.
决定联合举办博览会
The United States would show
what America was about
美方向苏联人民展示
to the Soviet public,
美国面貌
and the Soviet Union would show
what they were about to America.
苏方向美国公众展示苏联风采
And one of the centerpieces
were a series
重点活动之一是
of American kitchens,
一系列的美国厨房设备
and it was there
that Khrushchev and Nixon
当时赫鲁晓夫和尼克松
had their so-called
Kitchen Debate.
进行了所谓的厨房辩论
There are some instances
where you may be ahead of us.
也许在某些方面你们占优势
There may be some instances --
for example,
但某些方面
比如
color television --
where we're ahead of you.
彩色电视机
我们比你们强
But in order
for both of us --
为了我们双方的
[Speaking Russian]
For both of us
to benefit --
为我们双方利益考虑
for both of us to benefit --
FRANCO: But the U.S.
Information Agency
但美国新闻署
decided that they had to show
Russians more about America
决定向苏俄呈现 除了美国的汽车
than just cars
and household appliances.
和家庭用品以外的事物
KlRKHAM: The idea is that
Charles and Ray will make a film
当时的想法是由Charles和Ray
拍摄一部
about life in the USA:
"Glimpses of the USA."
关于美式生活的电影
名为 美国一览
How could you make the world
怎样才能让国外观众
as we see it
in the United States --
看到美国人民眼里的美国生活
how could you make it
really credible
怎样拍摄才能取信于国外观众
to an audience like that?
像苏俄人民那样的国外观众
We could've shown the greatest
freeway in the United States.
我们可以展示一张我们最好的高速公路的照片
If we'd shown one picture
and they'd gone,
如果把照片给他们看
而他们
they'd say, you know,
他们说
"They've got the great
freeway interchange,
他们有很棒的高速公路枢纽
but we've got one at Minsk,
但我们在明斯克也有这样的公路
and we're going to build one
at Smolensk,
而且我们将在斯摩棱斯克再建一条
and we'll have two,
and they have one."
这样我们就有两个了
而他们只有一个
But in the redundancy
of the multi-imagetechnique,
但在12秒钟冗长的
in something like 12 seconds,
多重图像技术中
I think we showed
120 freeway interchanges.
我们可以展现120个高速公路枢纽
ALBRECHT: People were sent
all overthe country.
大家被送到全国各地
Friends were called
to take images
也拜托各地朋友拍照
so that it looked
nationalistic.
好让照片看上去富有国家主义色彩
It couldn't look specific
and regional.
同时带有显著性和地域性
It had to be
national and egalitarian.
又必需具有民族主义且主张平等
LUClA EAMES: Charles said --
wanted pictures
Charles说 他想要的照片
of people setting off for work,
是关系人们出发去工作
children coming from school,
coming up from the subway.
孩子们下课回家
从地铁站出站
And freeways.
以及 高速公路
So I did my first,
所以 我第一次
you know, helicopterflights,
乘坐直升机飞行
sort of strapped in,
leaning way out.
系上安全带 把身子往外探
I think the State Department
had sort of envisioned
我想当时国务院提出过一些设想
having lots of troop marches.
加入很多部队行军场面
And Charles said
he'd do the film,
Charles回应
他拍摄这部影片
but he didn'twant to have it
reviewed before it was shown.
在公布之前不想被评论
JOHN NEUHART: The government
really didn't have any idea
政府方面对于影片的进展
whatwas happening.
毫不知情
We would have these showings
我们时不时地会给
for the guy who would represent
the government, coming out.
政府派来的代表
播放一些片断
It seemed like each time,
似乎每次放映
itwould just get going,
and then it'd go blank.
都只是播一小段
然后就黑屏了
And we'd say, "That's as far
as we are right now."
我们就说
我们就做到这么多了
And he'd say, "Well...
他说 好吧…
Yeah, I guess it looks okay.
行 我觉得看上去不错
I don't know."
我也说不好
So he'd go away.
然后他就走开了
DEMETRlOS: Well, as Charles
said, sometimes
就好像Charles说的
有时候
if you don't ask
for people's opinions,
如果你不跟别人征求意见
then they don't
give them to you.
他们就不会乱给你提意见
They just got there
the day before,
他们只是提前一天到场
and I think by that time,
我想到那时
the USlAwas just relieved
美国新闻署松了一口气
that there'd be anything
to show.
他们终于有东西可以拿出手了
ASHBY: You know, and here you
have this giant effort
你在这事上投入了巨大的努力
that'd gone into
building the building
场馆搭建好了
and putting the screens up,
银幕也设置好了
and tickets being --
all of that happening.
票也卖出去了
万事具备
And he's waiting
till the very last minute.
Charles等到开场的最后一分钟
It's just kind of his nature.
这就像是他会做的事
JOHN NEUHART:
Right at the end,
到最后
he would suddenly appear,
他会突然出现
and itwould look
like itwas effortless.
看上去毫不经意
He'd say, you know,
他会说
你们都知道
"This is just a little something
we've been doing."
这就是我们一直在做的一件小事
You know, and there'd be
blood all over the floor
接下来这段影片
from the thing, you know?
震撼了全场
CHARLES EAMES: When we look
atthe night sky,
当我们仰望夜空
these are the stars we see --
我们眼里闪烁的星星
the same stars that shine down
upon Russia each night.
同样在每一个夜里照耀着俄罗斯
We see the same clusters,
the same nebulae.
我们头顶是同样的星群和星云
And from the sky, it would be
difficult to distinguish
而如果从天空俯瞰
我们也难以辨别
the Russian city
from the American city.
俄罗斯和美国的城市
DEMETRlOS: If you're
going to communicate
如果你打算和三百万
with 3 million Soviet citizens,
you need to say something true.
苏联群众沟通
你必需得说点实话
You can't just show off
you've got
你不能炫耀
better weapons
or this or that.
你有更好的武器
如此等等
You've got to try to speak
from the heart, and they did.
你的话语必须由心而发
而他们做到了
Was it propaganda?
这是政治宣传吗
Goodness, yes, have you seen it?
天啊 没错 你没看见吗
Yes, it's, it's selling
the U.S.,
是的 这就是 兜售美国…
and it's selling, I think,
a very sanitized USA.
兜售 我觉得是政治审查润色过的美国
ALBRECHT: Of course
it was propaganda.
这当然是政治宣传了
They were Cold Warriors.
他们是冷战分子啊
The difference is they --
但事情的不同在于他们…
I believe they genuinely
believed it.
我相信他们真心买帐了
KlRKHAM: One of the interesting
things was how to end this.
如何收尾是个很有趣的问题
Charles had this idea
of a jet plane.
Charles有个关于喷气式飞机的想法
Ray still felt this might be
a bit hard-edged, a bit --
不过Ray觉得有点太强硬了
有点
could have
military implications.
军事影射的倾向
We never had an ending,
and one day Ray walked in
我们一直没有解决的办法
然后有一天Ray走进来
and said, "Forget-me-nots."
她说 勿忘我
Charles said,
"Okay, forget-me-nots."
Charles说 好的 就用勿忘我
FRANCO: Forget-me-nots,
勿忘我
the universal symbol
of friendship,
世界通用的友谊象征
translates directly
into Russian,
翻译成俄文
Nezabudki, "forget me not."
Nezabudki 勿忘我
KlRKHAM: They described
Nikita Khrushchev
当向赫鲁晓夫描述时
with tears
running down his cheeks.
他流下了热泪
So you have this wonderful
sort of double ending
影片有了一个双重意义的结尾
of the simplicity of a flower,
butthen this "Forget me not."
既是简单质朴的花朵
而花的名字又叫 勿忘我
And it worked
like the best Hollywood movie.
就像一部最棒的好莱坞电影一样
FRANCO: The Moscow show made
Charles and Ray newly famous,
莫斯科一役给Charles和Ray带来了新的知名度
not as designers of furniture,
but as communicators.
不是家俱设计师
而是沟通桥梁
Communicators who used images
ratherthan words.
他们用的不是语言
而是视觉印象
WECHSLER: Charles was
very wary of words.
Charles是出言谨慎的人
It's not about writing a script.
他的沟通方式不是编写剧本
It's about a sequence of images
而是用一系列的图像
that can tell a story.
讲述一个故事
FRANCO: In the Eames film
"Tops,"
在Eames的电影 陀螺 里
there are no words,
just pictures.
没有语言 只有图像
OPPEWALL: In a way,
the film is a kind of an essay
可以说 这部电影有点像一篇
aboutthe nature and meaning
of a top.
关于陀螺的特性与意义的随笔
In the beginning,
it's all aboutwinding up,
最初 你要缠好麻绳
getting started,
putting it together,
准备开始
收集必需用品
assembling the materials.
再把它组装起来
And then it's
aboutthrowing them,
然后把陀螺扔出去
seeing how they work,
what they do,
观察它们怎样运作
how they dance,
how they spin, how they sing,
如何起舞 旋转 歌唱
whatever it is
that their meaning is.
它们给人带来了怎样的启发
But then you come to one moment
接着切换到
where there's an architectural
plan on thetabletop,
桌面上放置着的一张建筑平面图
a blueprint,
and what spins
这是一张蓝图
而旋转着的
is a thumbtack, and you realize
是一颗图钉 你意识到
you have suddenly gotten
directly into the essence
你突然地了解了陀螺
of what it means to be a top.
所带来的意义的本质
Things have meaning,
things have personality,
事物都是有所涵义的
都是有个性的
things express ideas.
它们传达着创意和理念
Many designers were
and still are happy with
很多设计师的观念
the manipulation of objects.
依旧停留在操纵客体对象上
Hewas only truly deeply happy
Charles是仅有的 乐于沉湎于
manipulating an idea.
操纵创意的人
FRANCO: Beginning in the 1950s,
the idea ofthe computer
五十年代早期
电脑这一概念
triggered fear in the minds
of Americans.
触发了美国民众内心的恐惧
ALBRECHT: People were seeing
computers,
人们看到电脑后
and there was a worry
about them.
陷入了深深的忧虑
And this notion
of the electronic brain
这种电子大脑的概念
feeds into fears that we're
引进了 我们将要被
going to be taken over
by machines.
机器统治的恐慌
FRANCO: At the time, computers
were synonymous
那个年代 电脑是
with just one company -- lBM.
IBM公司的同义词
SELlGSOHN:
What was lBM's product?
当时IBM的产品有哪些
Big vacuum tube machines,
huge room-size machines,
大型真空电子管仪器
房间那么大的机器
building-size machines, so that
楼房那么大的机器
the average individual
was feeling an alien,
所以普通人往往感觉自己的隐私
science-fiction type
invasion of my privacy.
将遭受异己的 科幻片式的侵犯
How do you combat that?
这个问题应该怎样解决呢
FRANCO: lBM turned
to the Eames Office.
IBM求助于Eames工作室
To overcome the computer's
PR problem,
以解决电脑的公众接受度问题
Charles and Ray set out
to humanize it.
Charles和Ray着手于电脑的人格化
NARRATOR: Properly related,
it can maintain a balance
将电脑维护人的需要和资源
between man's needs
and his resources.
之间的平衡联很好地系起来
ALBRECHT: It's done in this,
这还挺成功的
what to us today
looks really corny --
以我们今天的眼光
会觉得有些老土乏味
but at the time, this was
thoughtto be radical --
但在那个年代
这种观念是很激进的
to do a film for a science
company, like a cartoon.
为科学企业制作电影 一个卡通片
NARRATOR: Something has now
emerged that might make
现有的科技也许能
even our most elegant theories
workable.
让我们最简炼的理论变得可以施行
ALBRECHT: And you go
from the abacus.
我们从算筹时代走来
As human problems
become more complex,
当人类面临的问题变得越来越复杂
people invent
more complicated machines
人们就会发明出更加复杂的机器
to solve those problems,
以解决问题
and the culmination of that is
the computer.
如此做到极致 就是电脑了
NARRATOR: This is a story
of a technique
这是一个科技服务于
in the service of mankind.
人类的故事
ALBRECHT: It's not
going to take over the world,
电脑并不会变成机器人
it's not going to be robots.
统治世界
It's the logical
evolutionary progression
这是一个人类不断改进产品
of man developing products
to solve problems.
以解决问题的 逻辑性进化过程
FRANCO: Charles's visionary
interest in computers
Charles在计算机上的远见
helped to bring lBM into
the Eames Office stables.
把IBM带进了Eames工作室
But it was not expertise
that made Charles and Ray
但并非Charles和Ray的专业知识
indispensible to
the rapidly growing company.
让他们成为IBM公司迅速发展壮大的因素
WURMAN: You sell your expertise,
如果把专业知识作为卖点
you have a limited repertoire.
实际上你的本领是有限的
You sell your ignorance,
it's an unlimited repertoire.
但如果把无知作为卖点
那么人的知识盲点是无穷无尽的
He was selling his ignorance
Charles利用的
and his desire to learn
about a subject.
正是自己对于电脑的无知
和学习的欲望
And the journey --
他所要做的
of him not knowing to knowing --
was his work.
正是从无知到知之
FRANCO: Over two decades,
Charles and Ray would complete
二十余年间
Charles和Ray为IBM完成了
dozens of projects,
large and small, for lBM.
大大小小几十个项目
But perhaps the most bold was
their pavilion
最为大胆的恐怕就是他们在
for the 1964 New York
World's Fair,
1964年纽约万国博览会为IBM设计的展馆了
a 1.2-acre experimental space
一个1.2英亩的超大实验型场地
celebrating the role
of computers in everyday life.
以颂扬计算机在日常生活中扮演的重要角色
ASHBY: I was drawing the stuff
我尽量让画草图的速度跟上
as fast as he
could conjure it up,
他思维的速度
and they came up with this idea
他们提出把展馆建在
of putting thattheater
up on top of these trees.
几棵树上的创意
And so I knew they were going to
have these plungers
所以我知道他们需要把那些
going into the ground --
they are going to move,
打入地面
才好让400名观众
you know,
400 people up on this ramp.
坐在斜坡的阶梯看台上
And I knew, as a designer,
I knew I was going to
我知道作为一名设计师
have to figure out some way
to make all that happen.
找到解决办法 使方案可行
And he's just so excited
about this thing.
Charles对这个创意感到十分兴奋
And I'm just standing there
like that.
我就那么在一边旁观着
And I said,
"Charles, this is just nuts."
我说 Charles，这也太疯狂了
And he says, "Yeah, and no one
had told us not to do it."
他说 是啊 可也没人让我们别这么干啊
FRANCO: For the show in Moscow,
they had used seven screens.
莫斯科展中
他们使用了七块屏幕
But at the lBM Pavilion,
there were 22.
但在IBM展馆 则使用了22块
CAPLAN: Charles was very big on
making people feel welcome.
Charles非常热衷于让观众感到宾至如归
You don'tjust get them in
an auditorium and showthe film.
你不能只是让他们坐到观众席上
再给他们放电影
You have a host.
你要有个主持人
But, uh, it was very hard.
不过 这还挺困难的
Everything you said not only had
to be memorized and rehearsed,
主持时所说的不一定非得是记过台本和排练过的
but it had to be timed,
重要的是每句话的时机
so when you pointed
to this screen,
当你指向一块屏幕
what you were talking about
appeared on this screen.
你口中谈论的和这块屏幕上显示的必须一致
And the same with that screen
and all the others.
另一块也是同样
每一块的解说都必须把握时机
Butthe problem was,
但是问题在于
the host
had a nervous breakdown.
压力太大 主持人精神崩溃了
FRANCO: As Charles and Ray's
reputation
随着Charles和Ray作为视觉沟通桥梁
as visual communicators grew,
的名声日渐壮大
so did their list
of corporate clients.
他们客户中的企业名单也越来越长
MAN: N is for...
N 代表着…
SlNGERS:
# Navigation equipment #
航海设备
# Network protectors #
网络保护装置
# Nuclear plant control #
核电站控制
# Nuclear reactor plants #
核反应堆工厂
# For surface ships
and submarines #
为水面舰艇和潜水艇服务
FRANCO: Westinghouse,
Boeing, and Polaroid
西屋电气、波音公司、宝丽来公司
all trusted the Eames Office
都放心地让Eames工作室
to solve their problems.
来解决他们的难题
When the Office was hired
by Alcoa
当美国铝业找到他们
to show off the uses
of aluminum,
为公司向大众展现铝的用途时
they built a solar-powered
Do-Nothing Machine,
他们造了一个太阳能“无为”机
which did exactly that.
这机器的的确确是啥也不干
SUSSMAN: That was
in the golden years,
那是个设计师的黄金年代
when the heads of corporations
would speak,
可以和一臂之遥的
a chair away from the designer.
企业负责人直接对话
So that if you needed
to talk to somebody,
所以如果你要和企业沟通
you talked
to the decision maker.
你可以和有权做决定的人交流
You didn't talk to a manager
who talked to a director
而不需要找到某个经理
经理再去找某个负责人
who talked to a chief director
负责人再去找某个主管
who talked to a vice president
主管再去找副总
who talked to
a senior vice president
副总再去找高级副总
who talked to
an executive vice president
高级副总再去找执行副总
who was allowed to talk to God.
执行副总才有权和终极大佬对话
SELlGSOHN: Almost never
was there a dissenting voice.
当时几乎没有不和谐之音
We trusted his decision making
entirely.
我们全心地信任他作的每一个决定
So his freedom to do
and to explain
所以他在思与行
and to conceive and execute
构想与决策
was almost unparalleled.
上的自由几乎是空前的
BEEBE: They didn't have
contracts.
他们不搞签合同这一套
They had a handshake.
握个手就把事情定下来了
All those huge projects
were done on a handshake.
所有那些大项目都是由握手敲定的
"We're going to give you
the best product,
“我们会给你们提供最好的服务
butwe can't tell you
what it's going to cost."
但你们得花多少钱现在还不好说”
And for lBM
对于IBM
and for Polaroid,
and for Herman Miller,
宝丽莱和Herman Miller这样的企业来说
it was okay.
这样的条件不成问题
FRANCO: And for Charles,
而对于Charles，
these gentlemen's agreements
went both ways.
这些君子协定却是把双刃剑
ASHBY: The budget for
"Mathematica" was $150,000.
纸面预算是15万美元
It actually ended up
costing $300,000,
到最后却得花掉30万
and Charles paid
for the $150,000
那多出的15万
that itwent over budget.
Charles得先自己解决
Sothe whole thing
aboutwhatthings cost
所以整件事 从做什么事要花多少钱
and trying to keep it
within the budget
到试图将花费节省在预算以内
and meet the clients,
he didn't care about --
再到超出后和客户协商
Charles根本不往心里去
he cared about it, but he just,
he couldn't stop himself.
也不能说他不在乎 但他就是
他就是控制不住自己
FRANCO: Charles and Ray's career
began with a utopian notion
Charles和Ray的职业生涯
始于一个乌托邦式的空想理念
of providing low-cost,
high-quality goods to the masses
即 在工业生产中 为大众提供
through industrial production.
质高价廉的商品
But they never viewed their work
但他们从未将服务于商业巨头
for corporate titans
as selling out.
视作背叛了当时的初衷
ALBRECHT: They wanted to work
for the Google of their time,
他们想为大公司工作
像今天的Google那样的的大企业
and they did, and it allowed
them incredible experimentation.
他们做到了 也得到了大展拳脚实验创意的机会
And they believed they could
have a bigger impact
他们相信 可以通过为更大的企业工作
on everyday life by working
for the bigger company.
来影响人们当下的日常生活
FRANCO:
lBM shared Charles's concern
IBM向公众传达了Charles对于
that American kids were falling
behind in math and science.
美国青少年在数学和科学方面
相对落后于其他国家的担忧
And as usual, they gave
the Office free rein
他们一如既往地给予了Eames工作室
to address the problem.
在处理这方面问题时的高度自主权
Maybe, Charles felt,
Charles觉得 也许
a film could help.
拍摄一部影片是不错的应对方法
NARRATOR: We begin
with a scene one meter wide,
which we view from just
one meter away.
Now, every ten seconds,
we will look
from ten times farther away,
and our field of view will be
ten times wider.
FRANCO: "Powers of Ten" would
become the best known
of all the Eames films,
viewed in countless classrooms
and copied freely by
filmmakers around the world.
SCHRADER: Everyone has seen
"Powers of Ten."
They may not have seen
the version Charles did,
but they have seen
one of the countless rip-offs
ofthat film.
NARRATOR: Ten to the sixth,
a one with six zeros,
a million meters --
soon the earth will show
as a solid sphere.
TONDREAU: Nobody had done
a movie like that.
How can you fail,
doing a cosmic zoom
in and out from all that is?
And so the concept is,
all by itself, mind-blowing.
NARRATOR: The trip back to
the picnic on the lakefront
will be a sped-up version,
reducing the distance
to the Earth's surface by one
power of ten every two seconds.
It's "Ch-ch-ch-ch-shoo,"
excessive information,
dizzying information.
NARRATOR: Ten to the ninth
meters,
ten to the eighth...
SCHRADER: Like in a chase
sequence in a movie,
everything is going by so fast,
it forces the observer to choose
the information
that's truly important,
which is the car
or the person
that is running away from you --
i.e., the idea.
NARRATOR: One. We are back
at our starting point.
SCHRADER: Eames was aware that,
in fact,
that this was somewhat dizzying,
and that it wasn't possible
to get all
of this information across
in a single viewing,
and that was fine.
What he probably didn't know
was that he was also looking
into the future
of audio-visual perception.
The pace at which we receive
information today
is as fast as he was doing
back then.
NARRATOR: As a single proton
fills our scene,
we reach the edge
of present understanding.
SUSSMAN: As time went on,
Charles became more and more
and more interested in ideas,
especially science
and mathematics.
Ray was less engaged.
I mean, I'm no mathematician,
and I'm no -- not an architect,
I'm not -- I haven't had
certain training,
so I just try to help in the way
that I -- in any way I can.
I don't stop to think
whether I can.
I just go as far as I can.
And if I --
if I can't, I can't.
TONDREAU: I think Ray
may have suffered
from a feeling
of marginalization,
because some
of those last projects
were heavy on ideas
and not as heavy
on the kind of visual richness
that was Ray's forte.
GlOVANNlNl: She's no longer
as instrumental
in the entire thing.
She can apply an aesthetic,
she can dress a set, and so on,
but, um, she's no longer
as central.
FRANCO: Ray's exquisite taste,
her eye for form and color,
made her indispensible
to the Office.
But it could also be
aterrible burden.
OPPEWALL: I remember peering
into Ray's office
only once or twice,
because when the door opened
and I looked into it,
I thought, "l don't everwant
to look in there again,
because it's a little
frightening."
ASHBY: Ray had a little room,
smallerthan Charles's,
directly across the hall
from his,
thatwas just
absolutely jammed
with all of her little
pieces of paper
and all of her little slides
and all of the little notes
that people had mailed to her
and that she was mailing
to them.
BEEBE: And she would go in
and find things.
She would say, "Oh, I have one,"
and she would disappear
into the room
and come out
with the perfect kite.
Or she'd go in and find
the perfect scarf or something.
Shewould go,
and she would fuss with it,
and change it one day,
and the next day,
she would look at it again
and change
a little something else.
And I think over the years,
the perfectionism
did get in the way.
In a way, it crippled her.
WOMAN: Here is oh, a picnic
basket, a drawing of a basket.
Up in Seaview Village,
so probably Deborah Sussman.
It's a letter
from Lily Saarinen.
That's cool.
Look at that,
I've never seen that.
There we go --
"Dearest Queen
of all Pack Rats."
I think it was almost
a nervous tic with her.
She was constantly
making notes,
and usually on the back of
Benson & Hedges wrappers.
This is one of the wrappers,
and on this side
she designed something
that looks very reminiscent
of some
of herfabric designs.
And you turn it over, and you
see it's a Benson & Hedges.
And on this side
are notes she made
for lighting ofthe puppet shows
at the lBM pavilion.
CAPLAN: You'd find them
everywhere.
They'd drive you crazy.
And they could say, "Buy soap,"
or "Liver and onions
for dinner,'
or they'd have
very elaborate ideas.
MARlLYN NEUHART:
She had her suits made,
and they had pockets that went
all the way to the hem.
So whatever she wanted to keep,
she would just shove
in the pockets.
MAN: So what would happen
with these notes?
McALEER: Well, for a time,
she asked the staff
to try to type them up,
and I think it became
too overwhelming
forthe staff.
It was such an avalanche
of notes.
TONDREAU: Ray didn't communicate
like everybody else does.
She expected that you
pre-understood
what she was talking about.
The people who didn't
make the effort
would sometimes use
the epithet "Crazy Rayzy,"
simply because they
didn't understand her.
But Ray is not crazy.
She's brilliant.
BEEBE: And Ray had
a lot of competition
for Charles's attention,
which I don't think anybody ever
really gave her credit for.
That everybody wanted Charles
and not Ray.
OPPEWALL: He was the guy that
the lBM executives would call.
He was the guy that you went to
to discuss the projects
intellectually.
He was very charismatic.
Charles was extremely
charismatic.
He was very charismatic.
He was very handsome.
He was very handsome
and very charismatic.
I know that word is really
overused, but he was.
And especially very charismatic
to women.
BLAlCH: He reminded me
of Henry Fonda,
and I met Henry Fonda one time,
and I told Henry Fonda this,
that I thought
they looked alike,
and he said,
"That's a compliment."
SUSSMAN: I mean, he had
these dimples,
and he -- "Aw, shucks,"
kind of guy.
SCHRADER: He was handsome
and smart, and cool.
So, you know, that's a kind of
lethal combination.
WECHSLER: It was the vision.
It was the personality.
It was the charm.
It was the unexpected.
It was the person.
This is just a small selection
of letters that I went through
to find things that pertain
particularly to the work.
"ln the next few weeks, I must
pull together a preliminary film
for the 'Franklin and Jefferson'
show."
And then the rest is personal.
BEEBE: I think their marriage,
it was a mystery to everybody,
in a way.
They were emotionally
extremely bonded.
But he found excitement
and thrills outside of Ray,
and outside of the Office,
which was really
crushing to her.
WECHSLER: I met him when he was
on the visiting committee
forthe architecture department
at M.I.T.
and I was a young
assistant professor.
Charles said, "Let's experiment
with some films on art."
I have many, many letters,
extraordinary letters.
Because we didn't live
in the same city,
we tried to see each other
as we could.
He had come to London,
and I was there,
and I could not get away.
And he said, "l will come
and stand in front of the house
at a certain time," and l
slipped out of this
ratherformal dinner,
and there he was, and we just
looked at each other.
We had a very profound love
for each other.
He wanted very much
for us to get married
and to have a child,
and to close --
he wanted to close
the Eames Office in Venice,
which he found very burdensome,
and for us to open an office
together in New York.
And I made a decision --
and I don't know if was
the right decision --
that I couldn't do it to Ray.
Because I had a friendship
with her,
but above all because they had
been together so long,
and I knew how much
she depended on him.
And I said, "l can't do it."
BEEBE: Ray dealtwith it
very privately.
Shewas hurt deeply,
but shewasn't
the kind of person
who would have said,
"It's me or her."
OPPEWALL: I don't think
she wanted to leave.
I think itwas something
that she had to accept.
This wasn't the era
of easy-come, easy-go
relationships.
There was too much
shared life and community,
and the fact that he, you know,
had other relationships outside
of the Office...
he seemed to be constructed
that way.
KlRKHAM: But there is a position
that I think is nonsense,
which is to say that because
Charles was having
a relationship
with somebody else
that he couldn't then carry on
a collaboration with Ray.
I mean,
that clearly didn't happen.
FRANCO: In fact, Charles and Ray
were about to collaborate
on the largest,
most complex project
the Office would
ever undertake.
For the nation's bicentennial
celebration in 1976,
the Eames Office designed
"The World
of Franklin and Jefferson,"
a traveling show made up
of three films,
40,000 words
translated into four languages,
and thousands of photographs
and objects,
including a stuffed bison.
When "Franklin and Jefferson"
opened in Paris,
it was seen by 50,000 people
in two months.
More than a thousand visitors
saw it each day
in London and Warsaw.
But when it came to New York,
the reception was different.
ALBRECHT: When it appeared at
the Metropolitan Museum of Art,
The New Yotk Times reviewed it,
and the headline was,
"What Is This Stuff
Doing at the Met?'
It was one of the first times
the Eameses were ever
criticized.
It had an enormous
amount of text.
Nobody could have possibly read
it all, it was so dense.
WURMAN: This show was
a bit picky for me,
too many little objects
that I would remember none.
It was too many things to see.
I can remember about ten things.
He knew so much
about all these things,
he couldn't edit out something.
These are things
of the period
and of the time,
from MountVernon.
WURMAN: They were all
so interesting to him,
and he was familiarwith them,
and he could see all these
connections.
But you can't keep it all
in your head
if you're not
that familiarwith it.
OPPEWALL: You could
call it clutter, butthat's not
what Charles
would have called it,
because clutter is
just stuff that's
dropped and abandoned
and forgotten and leftthere.
It was dense,
and it was complex,
but there was a mind at work
placing itthere.
Whether you as the recipient
were willing and able to accept
that is another question.
ALBRECHT: They're pushing up
against the envelope
ofwhattechnology could do,
because they're trying to give
the visitor
a hypertext experience,
but they're doing it
in physical space.
And it doesn'twork.
They are anticipating
what the computer can do today
very easily
with layering text and giving
you at different levels.
So it's a failure,
but it's an honest failure.
The criticism of
"Franklin and Jefferson"
hit Charles hard.
DEMETRlOS: The
"Franklin and Jefferson" show
was an exhausting show
because it was huge,
and I think sort of
the machinery of doing that
was just tiring.
TONDREAU: I saw Charles
at his happiest
when he was getting to do
a lot of photography.
And he was very engaged directly
on the creative process
of doing the photographs --
which led me to the idea
that maybe he felt
he was missing something,
you know,
because he had had
the transition
to more of an executive
position at the Office.
BEEBE: It was very hard for him,
because he didn't really have
a successor,
and for the years
that I was there, he was always
Iooking for the perfect person.
It was a battle one day
with the lBM representative,
Mike Sullivan,
and Mike said,
"Why don't you shutthis down?'
And he said, "I'd like to."
And Sullivan said,
"Whatwould you do?'
And he said, "I'd just travel
and shoot."
"But," he said, "l don't know
what to do about Ray,
and closing the Office."
BEEBE: He was tired, and he was,
I don't know if it was his
heart, but he was cold a lot.
I brought him one morning --
it was a Saturday morning,
and I'd made applesauce cake
or something,
and I brought it to the office,
and I handed it to Charles
wrapped in tin foil,
and itwas still warm,
and he took it,
pressed it to his chest,
and he was thrilled
to have that warmth
just sort of on his chest.
JOHN NEUHART: I was out of
the office the day that he died.
It was, in a way,
it was expected.
SUSSMAN: It just didn't
seem possible.
I mean, I knew that some people
that Charles worked with,
men in the East, wept.
He was such a dominant force in
the lives of designers that...
it was like there was suddenly
a big empty hole.
OPPEWALL: There are still days
when I'm driving
down the highway,
thinking about things,
and I think,
"Why did you die?
I'm notthrough with you yet!
I haven't finished asking you
the questions I wanted to ask."
He was the most important person
in my life.
I mean, he could be, he could
really be tough, you know,
but he...
he was an extraordinary
person.
BEEBE: After Charles died,
suddenly Ray was
the head of the Office.
She gathered everybody around,
and she talked about her goals
and what she wanted to do,
and how she needed
our help.
And it was really very powerful,
because she had never
donethat before.
But she feltthis huge burden
about carrying on the name
and carrying on the Office.
And I think itwas killing her.
And I said, "Come on, Ray,
why don't you
just close the Office,
and let's go and paint."
And she said
"No, that's all in the past.
I can't do that anymore."
FRANCO: Without Charles,
activity in the Eames Office
dwindled,
until it was time
to finally close 901.
Ray focused
on the painstaking work
of cataloguing the voluminous
40-year output
of the Eames Office.
Nearly 350,000 photographs
and half a million documents
had to be organized for shipment
to the Library of Congress.
But over the years,
a new generation
Iifted Ray
from Charles's shadow,
discovering in her
exuberant design sense
a refreshing alternative
to the austerity of modernism.
And Ray seemed to finally
find her voice
as one of the most influential
women of American design.
Best for the most for the least,
that was always the principle.
That's why we became interested
in mass production.
SUSSMAN: At that point,
women began to point to Ray.
You know, "lf there are
two Eameses,
why aren't they both credited?'
And now, of course, they are.
BEEBE: She kept saying, in
the hospital, "What day is it?'
And I would say,
"It's Wednesday the 18th."
And she would say, "Oh."
And then the next time
I would come,
then she would say,
"What day is it?'
"It's Thursday."
"Oh."
I think she wanted to die
on the same day as Charles
because it sort of symbolized
their being one.
Her last statement was one
of being with Charles.
This guy and that guy
could trade places.
There's probably an Eames chair
Iiterally in every single issue
thatwe've published.
You know, you could go
from the DAX to the DSS
to the LCW,
you know, you'll get
thiswhole range.
MAN:
Clockwise just a little.
Just a little.
Thefurniture still has
a quality
that every young designer
is searching for,
because of the amount of thought
that's been put into it
by everyone whose hands touch
the project.
I think you see that optimism
of the American spirit
in their design.
It provided
just a great blueprint
for how we could live our lives.
PEATROSS: What furniture
designers
ever have produced
40 to 50 pieces of furniture
that have been in production
for five decades?
Butthe other thing is
the sheer joy,
that aspect of play.
No one else, I think,
had that combination
of the pragmatic
and the aesthetic.
NARRATOR: Seven...
SUSSMAN: They loved to say,
"We don't do art.
We solve problems."
It's the process.
It's, how do we get
from where we are
to where we want to be?
NARRATOR: Grasp the rear
of the viewfinder...
DEMETRlOS: Charles and Ray were
always looking to the future.
They weren't
sort of sitting around,
telling war stories about
organic furniture.
What they were doing is like,
"What's the nextthing?'
ALBRECHT: They were there
for the major moments
in American history,
and they were really the
pioneers of the information age.
NARRATOR: The visitor
can try out the computer
as a carrier of information.
ALBRECHT: The breadth
of the work is extraordinary,
but there is also a unifying
theme of beauty
and a desire to reach
a broad audience.
So if it was pulled forward
a little bit?
Every designer owes them
some amount of debt,
but at the same time, part of
that debt should be to kind of
take what they did
and move beyond it.